A Guide to the Daniel Bedinger Lucas Papers 1859-1893 (bulk 1862-1864)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Daniel Bedinger Lucas Papers, 1859-1893 (bulk 1862-1864)
The Library of Virginia
42000
4.9 cu. ft. (9 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lilian B. Hagan, Roanoke, Virginia, through Ann F. H. Gladstone, Doswell, Virginia, 16 June 2005.
Biographical Information
Daniel Bedinger Lucas was born 16 March 1836 at "Rion Hall" in Charleston, West Virginia. He attended the University of Virginia and earned his law degree from Washington College in 1858. In 1861 he joined the staff of General Henry A. Wise and took part in the Kanawha Valley campaign, but a physical disability from a childhood spine injury kept him from active service in the last years of the war. Toward the end of the war he ran the blockade to defend his friend John Yates Beall, accused of being a Confederate spy. In 1867 he resumed his law practice in Charleston and married Evelina L. Brooke of Richmond in 1869. Lucas served as co-editor of the Baltimore Southern Metropolis and published many of his poems in the magazine. He became involved in Democratic party politics of West Virginia, serving in the West Virginia legislature from 1884 to 1887 and as a member of the Supreme Court of Appeals from 1889 to 1893. Lucas also wrote several volumes of poetry and was known as the "poet of the Shenandoah Valley." He died at Rion Hall on 24 June 1909.
Henry Alexander Wise was born 3 December 1806 in Accomack County, Virginia, to Major John Wise (d. 1812) and Sallie Cropper Wise (d. 1813). Wise attended Washington College in Pennsylvania, graduating in 1825. He then studied law under Henry St. George Tucker in Winchester, Virginia. Admitted to the Virginia bar in 1828, Wise followed his future wife and family to Nashville, Tennessee. He practiced law in Nashville for two years before returning to Accomack in 1830. Elected to the United States House of Representatives in 1833, Wise served until 1844. Wise was appointed Minister to Brazil in 1844, and served in that position until 1847. He represented the Eastern Shore counties of Accomack and Northampton in the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1850-1851, and represented Princess Anne County in the Virginia Secession Convention of 1861. Wise was elected governor of Virginia in 1855 and served from 1856 to 1860, during which time he met with John Brown (1800-1859) after the latter's failed raid in Harper's Ferry, (West) Virginia. During the Civil War, Wise raised troops and was appointed a brigadier general. After the war, he practiced law in Richmond, Virginia. Wise married three times: first, to Ann Elizabeth Jennings (1808-1837) of Nashville, Tennessee, 8 October 1828; second, to Sarah Sergeant (d. 1850) of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, November 1840; and third, to Mary Elizabeth Lyons (1817-1901) of Richmond, Virginia, 1 November 1853. He fathered fourteen children, only seven of whom reached maturity. Wise died 12 September 1876, and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1859-1893 (bulk 1862-1864), of Daniel Bedinger Lucas while serving on the staff of General Henry A. Wise. Includes correspondence, deserters reports, guard reports, maps, monthly and morning reports, muster rolls, orders, surgeons' reports and report of sick, and tri-monthly reports documenting the various regiments that served with the Wise Legion (or Wise Brigade).
Includes correspondence, 1861-1864, relating to the establishment of companies for Wise's Legion; and troop movements around Roanoke Island, North Carolina, and Richmond, Virginia. Of note are letters, 1864, relating to the movements and history of the Stono Scouts of South Carolina. Also included are General and Special Orders, 1861-1862, from Headquarters, Wise Brigade, Kanawha Court House and White Sulphur Springs, addressing the disposition of troops in Wise's Legion. Also of note is a letter, 9 June 1893, from Marcus J. Wright, War Records Office, Agent for the Collection of Confederate Records, to Daniel B. Lucas, regarding his loan of records for copying to the War Department in Washington, D.C.
The Wise Legion was organized during the summer of 1861 to serve with the Army of the Kanawha and was comprised of the 46th, 59th, and 60th Virginia Infantry Regiments, 10th Virginia Cavalry Regiment, and the Wise Legion Artillery. Throughout the war numerous companies were combined and reorganized in Wise's Legion, therefore included are records from several other military regiments. From 1862-1864 Wise's Legion served in South Carolina with the 6th Military District of South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida. Also included are records from the Confederate Light Artillery, Stark's Battalion; 4th Virginia Heavy Artillery Regiment; 15th Regiment and 32nd Battalion Virginia Cavalry; 2nd Regiment, 5th Regiment, 20th Regiment, and 26th Regiment Virginia Infantry; 2nd Regiment, 3rd Regiment, and Marion's Regiment South Carolina Artillery; 5th Regiment, 6th Regiment, and Stono Scouts Regiment South Carolina Cavalry; and Holcombe's South Carolina Legion.
Arrangement
Due to the varied sizes of the documents several Series may be in the same box. Each folder and box location is noted in the Guide.
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Confederate Light Artillery, Stark's Battalion (Battalion B, 1st Corps Artillery, Army of Northern Virginia)
Series II: Virginia Heavy Artillery Regiment, 4th
Series III: Virginia Cavalry, 10th Regiment, 15th Regiment, and 32nd Battalion
Series IV: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 2nd
Series V: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 5th
Series VI: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 20th
Series VII: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 26th
Series VIII: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 46th
Series IX: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 59th (2nd Regiment, Wise Legion)
Series X: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 60th
Series XI: Wise's Legion and 6th Military District of South Carolina (Department of South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida)
Series XII: South Carolina Artillery and Cavalry Regiments
Series XIII: Correspondence, Orders, and Miscellaneous
Contents List
- Series I: Confederate Light Artillery, Stark's Battalion, 1862-1863.
  - Morning reports, 1862 August. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Morning reports, 1862 September. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Morning reports, 1862 October. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Morning reports, 1862 December. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Morning reports, 1863 March. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Morning reports, 1863 April. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Morning reports (Captain Andrew D. Armistead's Battery), 1863 March-April. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Morning reports, 1863 May-September. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Surgeons' reports and Report of sick,1862 July-December. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Virginia Heavy Artillery Regiment, 4th, 1862-1863.
  - Bi-weekly reports, 1862 September-October. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Forage reports, 1862 August. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Guard reports, 1862 August. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Guard reports, 1862 September. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Guard reports, 1862 October. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Monthly reports, 1862 July-October. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Morning reports, 1862 August. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Morning reports, 1862 September. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Morning reports, 1862 October. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Morning reports, 1862 December. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Morning reports, 1863 March. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Morning reports, 1863 April. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Morning reports, 1863 May. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Morning reports, 1863 July. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Morning reports, 1863 August. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Morning reports, 1863 September. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Morning reports, 1863 October. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Substinence reports, 1862 August. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Surgeons' reports and Report of sick, 1862 August. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Surgeons' reports and Report of sick, 1862 September. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Surgeons' reports and Report of sick, 1862 October. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Surgeons' reports and Report of sick, 1862 December. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Surgeons' reports and Report of sick, 1863 March. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Surgeons' reports and Report of sick, 1863 April-May. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tri-weekly reports, 1862 September-October. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III: Virginia Cavalry, 10th Regiment (Company D), 15th Regiment (Company C), and 32nd Battalion, 1863.
  - Field returns and Morning reports, 1863 May-August. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1863 June. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 2nd, 1863.
  - 2nd Virginia Infantry Regiment, Monthly summary statements, 1863 June. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series V: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 5th, 1863.
  - Muster rolls (Companies A, C, D, F-I, K, L), 1863 October. (Map-case Cabinet 8, Drawer 10)
- Series VI: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 20th, 1862.
  - Monthly reports, 1862 September. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Morning reports, 1862 September-October. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series VII: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 26th, 1862-1863.
  - Commissary reports, 1862 August. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Deserters report, 1863 April. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Forage report, 1862 August. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Guard reports, 1862 August. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Guard reports, 1862 September. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Monthly reports, 1862 September-November. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Morning reports, 1862 August. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Morning reports, 1862 September. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Morning reports, 1862 October. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Morning reports, 1862 December. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Morning reports, 1863 March. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Morning reports, 1863 April. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Morning reports, 1863 May. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Morning reports, 1863 June. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Morning reports, 1863 July. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Morning reports, 1863 August. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Morning reports, 1863 September. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Morning reports, 1863 October. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Morning reports, 1863 November-December. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Ordnance and stores report, 1862 August. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Returns (Lieutenant Colonel J.C. Councill), 1862 December. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1862 June-August. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1862 September. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series VIII: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 46th, 1862-1864.
  - Guard reports, 1862 July-August. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Guard reports, 1862 September. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Guard reports, 1862 October. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Monthly reports/returns, 1862 September-November. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Morning reports, 1862 August. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Morning reports, 1862 September. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Morning reports, 1862 October. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Morning reports, 1862 December. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Morning reports, 1863 February-June. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Morning reports, 1863 July. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Morning reports, 1863 August. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Morning reports, 1863 September-November. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Morning reports (Companies G and I only), 1864 March. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Muster rolls (Companies A-D), 1864 March. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Muster rolls (Companies E-I, K)), 1864 March. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Muster rolls (Commissioned officers), 1864 March. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Muster rolls (Non-commissioned staff and band), 1864 March. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1862 August. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1862 September 1-14. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1862 September 15-30. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1862 October. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1862 December. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1863 February-April. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Tri-monthly report (Company A only), 1864 February. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series IX: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 59th (2nd Regiment, Wise Legion), 1861-1864.
  - Absentee reports, 1862 December. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Field returns, 1863 March-May. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    [Also includes information on the 32nd Battalion Virginia Cavalry; Colonel Holcombe's Legion; Captain Hawley's Company of 10th Regiment Virginia Cavalry; and a section of French's battery]
  - Monthly reports, 1862 September. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Monthly reports, 1864 February. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Morning report, 1861 August. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Morning reports, 1862 August-September. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Morning reports, 1862 October-December. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Morning reports, 1863 April-July. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Morning reports, 1863 August-September. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Morning reports, 1863 October-November. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Morning reports, 1864 February. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1862 December. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1863 March-May. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Tri-monthly reports, 1863 May. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    [Also includes section of French's battery, part of Stock's battery]
- Series X: Virginia Infantry Regiment, 60th, 1861.
  - Muster roll, Company G, Roane Rangers, 1861 July. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series XI: Wise's Legion and 6th Military District of South Carolina (Department of South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida), 1861-1864.
  - Conscripts assigned to Wise, 1863 January and February. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Consolidated morning reports, 1862 June-July. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Consolidated morning reports, 1862 August-September. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Consolidated morning reports, 1862 October-December. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Consolidated morning reports, 1863 January-May. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Consolidated morning reports, 1863 June-August. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Field returns, 1862 September. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Field returns, 1863 March-August. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Forage reports, 1861 July. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Ordnance reports and returns and Instructions to Ordnance Officers in the field, 1862 April; 1863 January, June-August. (Map-case Cabinet 8, Drawer 10)
  - Quartermaster reports, 1861 August. (Box 8, Folder 8a)
  - Regimental lists, 1861 June-August. (Box 8, Folder 8b)
  - Report of Heavy batteries, 1864 April. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Surgeon's reports and Report of sick, 1863 August. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Tri-monthly returns, 1863 August-November. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Tri-monthly returns, 1863 December. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Tri-monthly returns, 1864 January-February. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Tri-monthly returns, 1864 March-April. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Series XII: South Carolina Artillery and Cavalry Regiments, 1862-1864.
  - Subseries 1: South Carolina Artillery, 1863-1864.
    - South Carolina Artillery Regiment, 2nd, Muster rolls (Companies C-D), 1864 March-April. (Map-case Cabinet 8, Drawer 10)
    - South Carolina Artillery Regiment, 2nd, Semi-weekly and Tri-monthly returns (Company C), 1863 October-December. (Map-case Cabinet 8, Drawer 10)
    - South Carolina Palmetto Light Artillery Battalion, Company D, Muster roll, 1864 April. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - South Carolina Marion Light Artillery Battery, Parker's Company, Muster roll, 1864 April. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: South Carolina Cavalry, 1862-1864.
    - South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, 5th, Companies E and I, Muster roll, 1864 April. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, 5th, Company I, Tri-monthly report, 1863 December. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, 5th, Company E, Weekly return, 1863 December. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, 6th, Companies A and F, Muster roll, 1864 April. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, Captain Walpole's Company (Stono Scouts), Muster rolls, 1864 February, April. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, Holcombe Legion, Field returns, 1862 December; 1863 May-June. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, Holcombe Legion, Morning reports, 1863 April-September. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, Holcombe Legion, Muster rolls, 1863 April and undated. (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Series XIII: Correspondence, Orders, and Miscellaneous, ca. 1859-1893.
  - Correspondence, 1861 August-November. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1862 January-May. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1863 June. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1864 April. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Election results, ca. 1880. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - General and Special Orders, 1861-1862. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Map showing the battle grounds of the Chickahominy: and the positions of the subsequent engagements in the retreat of the Federal Army towards James River and all the other points of interest in connection with the siege of Richmond / from the most reliable information to be obtained by Edwin Sheppard, [1862?]. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Partial testimony of John E. Cook and Edwin Coppock regarding John Brown's Raid, ca. 1859. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Voucher, 1862 October 31. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Inventory and correspondence with Marcus J. Wright, War Records Office, War Department, Washington, D.C., 1893 June 10. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Inspectors certificate for the Steamer Philo Parsons (Detroit, MI), 1864 April 15. (Box 9, Folder 15)